Frances Cobb Todd papers, Inclusive: 1899-1990, undated, Bulk:1960-1990
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Frances Cobb Todd papers
Inclusive: 1899-1990, undated, Bulk:1960-1990
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
2960
Todd, Frances Cobb, 1931 - 1992
9 document boxes and 1 oversize box.
The Frances Cobb Todd papers represent the third generation of Smith-Cobb-Bledsoe family heritage and New Hope Baptist Church materials at The Texas Collection. The collection contains items from Todd's life and work in Waco and New Hope Baptist Church.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Frances Louise Cobb Todd was born in Waco, Texas, in 1930, to Eddie and Irene Caufield Cobb. The papers of Irene Caufield Cobb are also preserved at The Texas Collection. Frances Cobb Todd graduated from Waco High School, and went on to Bishop College in Marshall, Texas, where she graduated magna cum laude. She also received a master's degree from Prairie View A&M. On 1953 December 28 she married Emmitt Todd, who had also attended Bishop College. A scrapbook from their days together at Bishop is available in the collection.
After marriage, the Todd family lived and worked in Waco, Texas. Frances was a schoolteacher in the Waco Independent School District for over thirty years, and taught reading and language at Cedar Ridge Elementary, and Barron Springs Elementary. She was also very involved in community activities, such as Phi Delta Kappa, Waco Civic Theatre, Jack and Jill Incorporated, and her church, New Hope Baptist.
Emmitt and Frances Cobb Todd had one daughter, Alicia Todd Grinage. Alicia was very gifted musically, winning a number of awards for her piano playing. She attended Bishop College like her parents had, and received a degree in mathematics and computer science. She went on to receive a graduate mathematics degree from Howard University, and worked as a computer specialist for Texas Instruments and the United States Environmental Protection Agency. She married Robert James Grinage at New Hope Baptist Church in Waco on 1975 July 21.
Scope and Content
The Frances Cobb Todd papers begin in 1899 with a broadside from New Hope Baptist Church, and end in 1990. Most of the documents have to do with Todd's family life, church, teaching career, or the many organizations she joined.
Frances Cobb Todd, a Waco-area teacher for over thirty years, is also the third generation of Smith-Cobb-Bledsoe family members to have their materials preserved for research. Todd was also a member of New Hope Baptist Church, a church with a long heritage of service from the Smith-Cobb-Bledsoe families, and now the Todd family.
Arrangement
The Frances Cobb Todd papers were organized prior to this finding aid, with an existing finding aid. Many of the folder titles and arrangement already existing were kept. All of the folders were numbered, but some did not have folder titles.
Currently, the Frances Cobb Todd papers are arranged in three series: I. Personal Materials, II. New Hope Baptist Church, III. Organizations.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 2960. Acquired 1990-05-21
Related Resources
Items in related collections
Irene Cobb papers, Inclusive: 1886-1991, Bulk: 1960-1989
[Waco] New Hope Baptist Church records, Inclusive: 1875-1988, Bulk: 1922-1985
Smith-Cobb Family collection, Inclusive: 1861-1968, Bulk: 1948-1965
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
Moore High School (Waco, Tex.); New Hope Baptist Church (Waco, Tex.).
Subjects
African American Baptists -- Texas -- Waco.; African American churches -- Texas -- Waco.; African Americans -- Education (Higher).; African Americans -- Music.; African Americans -- Texas-- History; African-Americans -- Texas -- McLennan County.; Women -- Education -- United States -- History.
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Financial records.; Photographs.; Speeches.
- Personal Materials, 1930-1990, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  This series contains various materials on Todd's life, mostly organized topically, including letters, family materials from her daughter Alicia Todd Moss Grinage and others, photographs, and personal materials on Francis Cobb Todd.
  Index Terms
  Genres
  Photographic print
  - Correspondence, 1961-1990, undated; 1
    - General, 1971-1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - General, 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - General, 1983-1989, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - From Dee, 1972-1989 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - From Thelma, 1978-1990, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - From Alicia Todd Moss Grenage, 1961-1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - From Alicia Todd Moss Grenage, 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - From Alicia Todd Moss Grenage, 1977-1983, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Wedding Invitations: (1 of 3), 1973-1989 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Wedding Invitations: (3 of 3), 1973-1989 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Wedding Invitations: (3 of 3), 1973-1989 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Financial, 1972-1984, undated; 2
    - Bills, 1972-1984, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Literary Productions, 1925-1989, undated; 3
    - General, 1978-1986 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Memorial Resolutions, 1949-1976 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Memorial Resolutions, 1979-1987 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Religious Speeches, 1955-1972 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Religious Speeches, 1973-1979 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Religious Speeches, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Religious Speeches, 1983-1988 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Religious Speeches: (1 of 3), undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Religious Speeches: (2 of 3), undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Religious Speeches: (3 of 3), undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - General Programs, 1973-1989 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Religious Programs: (1 of 2), 1969-1988 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Religious Programs: (2 of 2), 1969-1988 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Religious Programs: Second Baptist Church, 1979-1988 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Religious Programs: Saint James United Methodist Church, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Religious Programs: Greater Mount Olive Baptist Church, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Religious Programs: Pleasant Grove Baptist Church, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Religious Programs: Trinity Baptist Church, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Religious Programs: Trinity Baptist Church, 1986-1988 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Religious Programs: Union Baptist District Association, 1975-1988 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Graduation Programs: (1 of 2), 1973-1988 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Graduation Programs: (2 of 2), 1973-1988 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Retirement Programs, 1973-1984 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Political Materials, 1980-1988 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Clippings: (1 of 3), 1954-1990 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Clippings: (2 of 3), 1954-1990 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Clippings: (3 of 3), 1954-1990 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Choir Music: (1 of 2), 1925-1931 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Choir Music: (2 of 2), 1925-1931 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Bishop College, 1930-1985 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Bishop College, Scrapbook, 1948-1950 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Church Women United of Waco, 1987-1988 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Joyce Stamps Day Nursery, 1972-1975 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Waco Independent School District Directory, 1976-1977 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Francis Cobb Todd School and Teaching, 1954-1984 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Francis Cobb Todd Retirement, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Alicia Todd Moss Grinage, 1965-1990; 4
    - General, 1965-1976 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Clippings, 1972-1990 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Essays, 1966-1968 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Cobb Family Reunions, 1983-1988; 5
    - 3th, 4th Celebrations, 1983-1986 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - 5th Celebration, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Genealogy, 1981-1989; 6
    - Cobb Family, Caufield Family, 1981-1989 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Eddie Cobb, Jr., 1986-1988; 7
    - General, 1986-1988 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbooks, 1948; 8
    - A.J. Moore High School, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Death of Francis S. Martin, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Photographs, 1929-1986, undated; 9
    - General, 1947-1986 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - General: (1 of 5), undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - General: (2 of 5), undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - General: (3 of 5), undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - General: (4 of 5), undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - General: (5 of 5), undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Francis Cobb Todd, 1939-1983 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Francis Cobb Todd at Cedar Ridge School, 1945-1980 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Alicia Todd Moss Grenage, 1972-1981, undated (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Wedding of Elien Felice Moss and Alicia Todd Moss: (1 of 3), 1978 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Wedding of Elien Felice Moss and Alicia Todd Moss: (2 of 3), 1978 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Wedding of Elien Felice Moss and Alicia Todd Moss: (3 of 3), 1978 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Irene Cobb, 1929-1950, undated (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Jean Cobb, 1948-1950, undated (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Family Reunion, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Cookout, 1947-1948 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Carlsbad Caverns, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Los Angeles, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - San Angelo, 1948 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Cameron Park, 1950, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Military, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - A.J. Moore High School, 1948 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - School Field Day, 1947-1948 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - School Yearbook: (1 of 3), 1944-1948 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - School Yearbook: (2 of 3), 1944-1948 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - School Yearbook: (3 of 3), 1944-1948 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - St. James Methodist Church, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
- New Hope Baptist Church, 1899-1990; 2
  This series contains materials collected by Francis Cobb Todd about New Hope Baptist Church, including church worship bulletins, various church programs, and photographs.
  - Programs, 1952-1990; 2
    - General: (1 of 6), 1952-1990 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - General: (2 of 6), 1952-1990 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - General: (3 of 6), 1952-1990 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - General: (4 of 6), 1952-1990 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - General: (5 of 6), 1952-1990 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - General: (6 of 6), 1952-1990 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Church Anniversaries, 1975-1983 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Church Anniversaries, 1987-1990 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Church Anniversaries, 1975-1990; 3
    - General, 1975-1983 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - General, 1987-1990 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Church Bulletins, 1952-1989; 4
    - (1 of 4), 1952-1989 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - (2 of 4), 1952-1989 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - (3 of 4), 1952-1989 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - (4 of 4), 1952-1989 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Photographs, 1956-1983; 5
    - General, 1975, undated (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Choirs, 1976-1981, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Groups and Committees, 1966-1976, undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Groups and Committees, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Parsonage, 1956 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Church Anniverssary, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Vacation Bible School, undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - High School Graduation (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Sunday School (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Historical Marker Dedication, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Buildings, circa 1952 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Administrative Records, 1899-1990; 1
    - General, 1899-1989 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, 1979-1989 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Church Governance, 1916 (copy)-1990 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Stained Glass Windows, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Membership Directories, 1971-1979 (Box 6, Folder 16)
- Organizations, 1960-1989; 3
  This series contains materials on various civic organizations that Francis Cobb Todd joined. In 1973, Todd was vice-president of the Waco chapter of the Jack and Jill Incorporated organization. She was also the first African American woman to serve on Waco Civic Theatre board of directors.
  - Various Organizations, 1962-1989; 1
    - (1 of 2), 1962-1989 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - (2 of 2), 1962-1989 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - J.O.A. Conner Study Club, 1968-1984; 2
    - (1 of 3), 1968-1984 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - (2 of 3), 1968-1984 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - (3 of 3), 1968-1984 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Waco Civic Theatre, 1986-1988; 3
    - (1 of 3), 1986-1988 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - (2 of 3), 1986-1988 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - (3 of 3), 1986-1988 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Phi Delta Kappa, 1975-1989; 4
    - National Materials, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - National Materials, 1987 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Regional Materials, 1983-1985 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Local Organization: (1 of 4), 1975-1989 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Local Organization: (2 of 4), 1975-1989 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Local Organization: (3 of 4), 1975-1989 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Local Organization: (4 of 4), 1975-1989 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Scrapbook, 1973-1977 (Box 10 OVZ, Folder 2)
  - Alpha Kappa Alpha, 1969-1982; 5
    - General, 1969-1982 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Jack and Jill Incorporated, 1972-1988; 6
    - (1 of 4), 1972-1988 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - (2 of 4), 1972-1988 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - (3 of 4), 1972-1988 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - (4 of 4), 1972-1988 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Scrapbook, 1973 (Box 10 OVZ, Folder 1)
  - Various Teaching Organizations, 1960-1989; 7
    - General, 1960-1989 (Box 9, Folder 12)